I'm here to answer the age-old question.
If you grow a tiny brain from human stem
cells, does it need to sleep? And what
happens if you give it fatal familial
insomnia? I don't know if this was my
age-old question, but I have answers
now. First off, you can create an brain
organoid that has a hypothalamus, either
an entire hypothalamus organoid or just
put them together like Legos, so it
includes one. That can also be done at
the brain stem. A hypothalamus is a part
of your brain that helps regulate things
like sleep and circadian rhythm. If it
doesn't work, you may never sleep again.
It turns out your individual neurons
know what time it is. Brain organoids
went through circadian rhythm in which
they produce clock proteins. That's a
protein in your body that is associated
with a cascade of events that puts you
to sleep and regulates other autonomic
functions. And the researchers wanted to
know if it could be disrupted not unlike
how we disrupt our own sleep schedules.
If they gave it cortisol in the
afternoon to simulate a night shift, it
would completely disregulate their
circadian rhythm. They would produce
less clock proteins and in some cases
stop producing them at all. They also
tried cooling and heating them because
your body usually cools down when you're
going to sleep and it had a very similar
effect. Turns out every cell in the
brain already knows what time it is,
whether or not it has the hypothalamus.
But what of fatal familial insomnia? A
condition that causes people to slowly
lose the ability to sleep and ultimately
expire sleep is kind of important. Turns
out, yes, brain organoids can get it and
it does disrupt sleep. Giving brain
organoids fatal familial insomnia may
have taught us a lot about the actual
treatment of the condition. You see,
brain organoids don't really sleep. They
have something akin to a circadian
rhythm, but they largely only give us
delta brain waves, meaning they're
essentially always in a sleeping state.
Fatal familial insomnia is a pryion
disorder in which proteins end up
sticking together and turning other
proteins inside out and they form
plaques in the brain and this condition
is primarily in the hypothalamus.
When you give brain organoids it, it
affects them too. It forms plaques in
them but it also keeps neurons from
effectively communicating with each
other. Meaning even if you are something
that doesn't really have a sleepwake
cycle, you still have issues with your
neurons functioning if you got the
condition. That means it's likely more
than just sleep. Although not sleeping
is not great. People who have fatal
familial insomnia start slowly being
able to lose their ability to sleep and
then they can never sleep again. And
that's that's not great. I hope I've
imparted on you guys that brain
organoids are more than just creepy.
They actually do a whole lot of good and
allow us to study conditions that we
would never be able to have access to
because we don't experiment on people.
They're not conscious. Not yet at least.
I am slightly concerned about the
direction that this research is going
in. But I'm not the only one. There have
been calls to make a regulatory body
internationally to make sure that brain
organoid research is done ethically. If
we do eventually accidentally make
consciousness, we really should have
laws about it before we get there. In
the meantime, brain organoids are going
to do a whole lot of good. It just
they're a little spooky. I get it. If
you like my content, you may follow and
like for more. I probably will still
tell you about it whether you like it or
not. I'm a little bit hard to avoid.